[music]
Now it's time for the Anchormen podcast
with Matt Gates and Pearson [music]
Sharp.
Welcome back to another episode of
Anchormen. We are so excited uh that we
are going to be able to bring you such a
level of expertise and insight in this
program. I'm joined as always by my
co-host at Pearson Sharp, host of the
Sharp Report here on our network. And
the building is a buzz because we've got
John Kuryaka with us for uh an hour and
uh we so many of our producers whenever
we book John on the Mac Gates show uh
everyone's excited. Everybody wants to
contribute to the discussion because we
always learn a great deal. John Kiryaku
was a a CIA officer in the leadup to 911
then takes major roles within the CIA
counter intelligence in 2007. famously
becomes part of this major disclosure
that torture is being uh administered by
the United States government. John later
plead guilty to a crime revol involving
disclosure of information. Uh he uh was
sentenced to 30 months. He got out after
two years and really has been heralded
by many as a whistleblower, as someone
who saw things going on in the
government that uh the the country
wasn't aware of, people weren't aware
of, and uh you know, has been really out
there. John, thanks so much for joining
us. Uh I've had I've really enjoyed
having you on the Matt Gates show uh
talking about
>> It's been my pleasure. Lots of fun.
>> Well, you're a really smart guy. You've
lived an incredible life. Uh my co-host
and and buddy here, Pearson Sharp, has
been all over some of these things we've
seen in the headlines and wants to ask
you about them. So, go right ahead,
Pearson.
>> Hey, John. How you doing?
>> Good to see you.
>> Good. So, did you see the news that came
out about uh the vaccines and the CIA
operations recently?
>> Yeah.
>> Um so, apparently it was called Project
Artichoke. And for anyone who's not
familiar, apparently it ran from 1951 to
1956. and it focused on uh behavior
control, interrogation techniques, uh
psychological manipulation, but the
interesting part that got everybody
paying attention was the fact that it
was being administered through
injections and vaccines.
That was the big one. And um I want to
know what your take on on that was do
you know anything about it? What's your
thoughts?
>> Oh yeah. Project Artichoke was a sub
operation of MK Ultra which by now most
Americans know that MK Ultra was
experimentation essentially on American
citizens mostly using LSD. There were a
bunch of sub operations here, project
artichoke being one, where the CIA began
by experimenting on its own employees.
And after that didn't go well, they
began experimenting on just innocent
residents of San Francisco. What they
did as part of Project Artichoke was to
break into um a um
a vaccine developer in Switzerland,
steal the formula for some of the
vaccines, and then tried to manipulate
the formula so that they could give
somebody a vaccine, have it act like a
truth serum, and then get these people
to involuntarily tell the truth. with
the idea being that you would use it on
Russians and Chinese. The way this all
got started in the very early 1950s is
there was the CIA recruited a Soviet uh
intelligence officer KB KGB officer who
told him that who told the agency rather
that the Russians were developing this
kind of technology. That was not true.
The Russians were not developing that
technology. the Chinese were, but we
didn't know that the Chinese were. And
so the CIA panicked and said, "Well,
we've got to beat the Russians to this
uh to this technology, this science."
And so they started this
experimentation, as I said, first on
their own employees and then on just
innocent Americans. As part of of uh
Operation Artichoke, one of the things
they did was they recruited a bunch of
prostitutes in uh San Francisco. They
rented a safe house where the
prostitutes would bring the John's back.
They would dose the John's with LSD and
then try to get them to reveal their
innermost secrets under the the
influence of the LSD. I don't mean to
smile.
>> By the way, by the way, there's plenty
of people that you wouldn't even have
had to trick to do that.
>> Yeah, they [laughter] sign up for that,
>> right? It's like, you know, prostitutes
and LSD. There'd be there's some places
in San Francisco [laughter] there'd be a
long line of volunteers.
Isn't that the truth? Um,
>> so this thing went on for years, for
years, and then when it was finally
revealed in the church committee
hearings in 1975,
um, the CIA director was ordered not to
destroy the documents. And he went back
from Capitol Hill and ordered the
destruction of all the documents. And so
what we what we know now is is from the
15% of documents that survive.
>> Yeah. Um, one of the things that was
they said was also the goal was to coers
people into committing criminal acts
against their will, potentially
including assassinations.
And unrelated to this, I just came
across an article recently about uh
Charles Wittman. Are you familiar with
him?
>> I don't know that name. So, in uh 1966,
Charles Whitman, who was just the most
upstanding, patriotic guy you could
possibly imagine, had an IQ of 138,
former Marine, uh married, had a family,
suddenly decided that he was going to
kill his wife in the middle of the
night, kill his mother as well, and then
climb the tower at the University of
Texas in Austin,
>> and with a sniper rifle, kill 13 people,
including pregnant women and a bunch of
others. And he left a suicide note
behind that said, "I have no idea why
I'm doing this. I don't want to do it.
It doesn't feel like me. I I can't stop
myself. I I hope that when I do it and I
die that someone will cut open my brain
and, you know, see what happens." Like,
is there something wrong with me because
I can't stop myself from doing this. Um,
apparently there was like a tumor or
something that had grown and was pushing
on his amydala.
But this guy seems like the exact kind
of case that you would see from a
project like Artichoke or MK Ultra. I
was just curious what your thoughts
were.
>> Well, you have to ask yourself too, you
know, there were references to Los
Angeles County Community College in the
MK Ultra documents. There was some kind
of experimentation going on at the LA
community college and it just so
happened to be exactly the same time
that Sirhan Sirhan was taking classes
there. And so there's been speculation
over the years that Sirhan may have
either volunteered to be a part of these
um these experiments for money or was
you know tricked or somehow duped into
taking part of the experiments because
he too later said and he's been
relatively consistent about this that he
doesn't know why he killed Bobby
Kennedy. He doesn't have any memory of
killing Bobby Kennedy. And
>> well that was one of the goals was
they'd have no memory of doing the
things.
>> Exactly. And you know that gave rise to
the whole Manurion candidate fear in the
1950s.
I
>> if this technology was being developed
um what was its end point and is it is
it is it a working assumption that these
types of programs and activities are
ongoing today or or did we reach some
reckoning on on these tactics?
>> That's what I want to know because
that's why I asked John. That's that's
our fear is that we've seen them using
vaccines for this project artichoke and
after 2020 I think a lot of us were
concerned what's going in these
vaccines. Why are why is everybody
demanding that we take these vaccines?
What is going on here? And so yeah with
MK Ultra and this we know the government
does this. We know they lie to us. We
know they inject us with things that we
don't willingly consent to. So what are
your thoughts on that?
>> Yeah. And isn't it ironic that the
government just tells us, "Take our word
for it, right? We're the experts."
>> Of course.
>> Yeah. We're the experts. Well, you know,
I I don't mean to sound cynical, but I I
almost can't help myself after the
odyssey that my life has been over the
last 25 years, but um you know, we've
got the House Permanent Select Committee
on Intelligence and the Senate Select
Committee on Intelligence. These are
supposed to be the the two oversight
committees, and they're really not
oversight committees so much as they are
cheerleaders for the CIA. So, we've been
told that MK Ultra and all of its
associated sub operations ended by 1975.
How do we know that? We don't know it.
We're just supposed to take their word
for it and trust these cheerleaders,
senators, and congressmen
uh with for with telling the truth that
these programs don't exist any any
longer. But you know what though, even
if they do exist, they would be so
tightly controlled, so compartmentalized
that only the gang of four or the gang
of eight would uh would have access to
the information anyway. And it would be
so highly classified that they wouldn't
be able to say anything. Do you think do
you think Trump knows?
>> No, I don't.
>> So, uh, I can confirm your concerns
about how people get on those
committees. Uh, the the, uh, usual way a
committee is populated is by a steering
committee. We have, of course, in
Congress, we have a committee on
committees. Uh, and it democratizes
power. It dilutes power. So, you know,
ostensibly if you talk to a lot of
members, you could get on the armed
services committee, you could get on the
agriculture committee, but the
intelligence committee is unique. It is
direct appointment by the speaker of the
house. The speaker of the house hires
and fires every member of the
intelligence committee. And what that
turns into is the intelligence community
selecting their own overseers. Uh, I
remember what a what a coup it was to
get Congressman Scott Perry on the
intelligence committee and we kind of
had to leverage Speaker Johnson on that
one a little bit. We had to tell Speaker
Johnson that if he wanted an outcome a
certain way on the floor with the votes,
we needed to see Scott Perry on uh on
the intelligence committee that would
give us confidence. And when we did,
because he wasn't he was picked by us,
not by the IC, the attacks on him, the
op-eds written about this is a guy who's
a general and and and they couldn't they
couldn't take it because
>> he wasn't part of the club.
>> They want to know, I frankly think they
want to know they want to hold
compromising information over the people
that are on those committees, but they
certainly want to know that they're on
the team and are not going to ask ask
too many questions. And John, you know,
did you have other questions about
artich choke? Uh, no. Go ahead. Yeah.
So, I
>> before before, Congressman, before you
ask your question, may I add one little
thing just to sort of prove to prove
your point?
>> A couple of weeks after I got out of
prison, I was invited to dinner at the
at the Greek ambassador's residence. So,
I went and there was a Democratic
senator there from the Senate
Intelligence Committee and he walked up
to me and he said, "Hey, welcome home.
we were so worried about you. I said,
"Thanks, Senator, but I got to tell you,
I was disappointed. I thought I thought
you would stand up for me." And he got
angry. And he said, "Look, it took
everything I had just to not lose my
security clearance." And I said, "Oh,
you're afraid of them." And then he just
walked away from me.
So what you're saying is exactly true.
>> Yeah. It's I I saw it and the the the
unique opportunity though is one person
can put people on and take people off.
And so if you if you play the game right
and utilize leverage right, there are
opportunities to get eyes on some of
this.
>> I mean John, you said he was afraid the
people in power, the highest people in
power are afraid of these people.
>> Yes.
>> How should the rest of us feel?
>> I know, right? Right. some system we've
given ourselves and and we all thought
that was going to change in 1975 and it
changed for a minute and then by 1982
you know the CIA was the old CIA again
doing the same CIA things it was doing
in the '50
>> but but it it does suffer from some of
the like normal bureaucracy stuff that
is common to all of the agencies in
Washington. I had a CIA uh person who's
still still with the agency who said,
"Matt, everybody thinks it's all Jack
Bower, but it's way more the office."
Uh, comment to like comment to that,
John. I mean, how this it's this
mystical force that people um you know,
opine about, but but you were inside the
belly of the beast. Is it is it more
Jack Bower or more The Office?
>> Oh, it's decidedly more The Office. We
used to have this ongoing joke that when
you went into a meeting, don't touch the
table because you don't know who was
having sex on it last night.
>> Um,
>> I thought that was going to be a
fingerprints reference.
>> That's true in Congress now, too.
>> Well, in the committee hearing rooms.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Yikes, man. Total lack of creativity.
>> John John F. Kennedy once called the CIA
the best and the brightest. And oh, how
I wish that were true. Um, yes, there
are some really brilliant people in
there. And for the most part, these are
these are whatever it is now, 30 40,000
people who who want nothing more than to
serve the American people. But without
appropriate oversight, you know, it's
human nature just to push and push and
push the envelope until somebody or
something pushes back. And as a result,
you have a CIA that, you know, in a
cycle of every 20 or [clears throat] 30
years, it goes out of control.
>> You've heard me talk about all family
pharmacy before. I'm going to keep
talking about my great friends there
because they're doing things the right
way. They are fast, reliable, and they
actually care about getting people
medications they need without the usual
crazy runaround. So, if you don't want
to wait in line for your medications, if
you don't want to have to fight with
your doctor, you just need to go to
allfamilyfar pharmacy.com/matt.
when everyone else around you is sick,
you will be prepared. Now, uh they've
got a great opportunity going on. If you
enter code Matt 10, you get 10% off your
order. You need all family pharmacy.
They've got everything. Antibiotics,
antivirals, tamlu, ivormectin,
hydroxychloricquin, blood pressure
medications, vitamins, daily maintenance
meds, so much more. Order online. Their
doctor will approve it and it'll come
right to you. So, if you're tired of
this broken health care system, choose
the right pharmacy. Go to allfamilyfarm
pharmacy.com/matt.
Use code matt10 to save 10% off your
next order.
>> There was a there was a great comic and
maybe we can find it. Um I saw of when
the CIA was created, it showed the
president holding a little puppy on a
leash and it said like 10 years later it
flashed forward and it was this like
giant pitbull that was attacking the
president. And like if you know history,
I was thinking back to Rome when the
Ptorian guard basically took over Rome
and they were picking and choosing the
emperors and running things behind the
show. And I'm wondering, is that what's
happening now? Is the CIA and and these
secret organizations actually in charge
of everything?
>> You know, I hate to say yes, but but my
answer's got to be yes. And I I'll give
you one one example, too. Um I I was
stationed overseas and I had to do a
very sensitive counterterrorism
approach. It was to a woman and she was
a a known bomber, shooter. This was a
bad bad woman. Well, she had been
approached once before, 20 years
earlier, by a guy who later went on to
be a senior station chief, you know,
senior intelligence service. So, he was
a friend of mine and I sent him a cable
and I said, "Listen, I'm going to do
this high threat approach, but you've
spoken to her once before. She'll
remember you. Can you fly out here and
do the approach with me so she doesn't
feel threatened?" So, he flew out and we
were doing a foot surveillance detection
route. It was a very heavily populated
city. So, we're doing our surveillance
detection route by by foot. And his cell
phone rings and it was the president of
the country that he was serving in as
the station chief. And I heard him say,
"Yes, madam president. Yes, madame
president." And this is going on for a
minute or two. And he says, "Well, my
choice is and then he names a name." And
uh I could hear Madame President say,
"Thank you so much for taking care of
this." this and she hung up and I said,
"What was all that about?" And he said,
"That was the president of, you know,
the country." I said, "What' she want?"
He said, "Uh, she wanted me to choose
the next intelligence service director."
So, I chose my guy.
>> And I said, "We do that."
>> Oh, yeah. We do. We definitely still do
that. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, as a congressman, I weighed in on on
who I thought should be in intelligence
services in foreign government. We want
him to be on team America. We want him
to be for uncle. had we had Victoria
Nuland picking the next prime minister
of Ukraine. I mean
>> exactly right. Yes.
>> This is this is how this is how politics
works in a globalized age. Don't don't
hen ring about that. But John, you moved
up in this system. You went from a CIA
officer to someone who had major
responsibilities. You know, I I think
people know know you as a whistleblower,
but before that moment, you really did
play the game right and accumulate
power. And so talk to us about uh maybe
an experience or or an anecdote that
showcases how within that system you
thrived.
>> Oh, I did. I I'll tell you the truth. I
was a true believer for many many years
and uh I was smart. I was a good
briefer. I was willing to take the worst
assignments. I was willing to go to the
worst countries. I've been to 72
countries over the years and I was very
happy to do it. Um yeah, I'll give you
an example. Uh I um I got a call once
from a friend who was a CIA station
chief in the Middle East and he said
that uh that one of his officers had had
recruited a double agent and this was a
double agent for a major enemy of the
United States. It not not hard to guess
who. And so uh the guy insisted on
meeting with the station chief. He said,
"Could you come out here and uh and
pretend to be me and handle this double
agent?" I said, "Of course." So, I
started flying out to the Middle East
every couple of weeks, meeting with this
guy, giving him assignments, and then
all the while, as soon as we leave the
meeting, he's on the phone with his
other handlers reporting uh what uh what
they wanted him to report. It got to the
point where I was I was home at
headquarters and I got a call from
a sister agency on the other side of the
of the city and um they said, "Are you
handling this double agent in the Middle
East?" And I said, "Yeah." And the woman
said, "You should know that they just
ordered him to kill you in the next
meeting." I said, "Oh, please. This
guy's afraid of his shadow. He's not
going to kill me." My boss comes running
out of his office. You got to abort the
operation. He's going to kill you. I
said, "Please hear me out." At least to
make a long story short, I flew back
out.
I was able to tackle him as he entered
the the hotel room. Our liaison partners
burst in from the from the next door
room. All while this guy is shouting,
"Allah abbar, Allah Akbar." And I'm I'm
disarming him and I'm sitting on his
chest and I said to him, "Did you really
think I was so stupid that I didn't know
that you were a double agent all this
time? Did you really think I was such an
amateur that I didn't know that you came
here to kill me today?" I said, "I'm
offended." Well, that was 24 years, 25
years ago. He's still in prison and uh
we dismantled
dismantled a terrorist group in that
country because of that arrest.
>> Incredible.
>> But I I was perfectly happy to volunteer
and go anywhere in the world to do
operations like that. And so I moved up
quickly to the point where I became the
the uh executive assistant to the CIA's
deputy director for operations. It was
in that position that I finally had
access to literally everything that the
CIA was doing around the world. And some
of it was just wrong, wrong, wrong.
>> Well, you know, I understand I know
there's only so much you can you can
sort of talk about that stuff, but let's
c let's talk about the category of
wrong, you know, because cuz some people
[clears throat] would say, oh, yeah,
maybe wrong is, you know, deceiving
someone, lying to someone to get them to
do what you want them to do. Maybe wrong
is threatening someone um threatening
their family. Um you know, maybe wrong
is like the stuff we've seen uh in the
Epstein files where where real people
are enduring incredible harm and the
people who are administering that harm
believe it is in service of some of some
broader virtuous goal like put put the
harm in buckets for us.
>> Yes. I was unwilling to break US law.
Listen, when you're a CIA officer, your
job is to break the law. It's to break
the laws of other countries. I was
thrilled to get on a plane, go overseas,
and commit espionage. That's what I was
paid to do. And it was fun, and it was
rewarding. But I drew the line where it
came to breaking US law. And I said to
my my superiors at the time in in the
middle of 2002, we have something called
the Federal Torture Act of 1946, which
specifically prohibits us from doing
exactly the things that you're telling
me we're going to start doing. Plus, not
only were we signitories to the United
Nations Convention Against Torture, we
wrote the United Nations Convention
Against Torture, and it was uh uh
>> clear that was a law for everybody else.
>> Yeah. Right. And so,
>> but torture at the time was romanticized
in interrogation. Yeah. No, but it was
uh you 24 was the affforementioned 24
was one of these iconic television shows
and you always rooted for Jack Bower to
to to administer pain on the bad guy
until they gave the critical information
and it in in Hollywood torture worked in
Hollywood. It worked in Hollywood. Is
that was was that not your experience in
the CIA? That was a big problem for us
actually through through the as uh
because torture had been romanticized.
Americans did come to believe that
torture worked. You know, I'll tell you
a little side story. After I led after I
left the CIA, I uh I was uh made an
adjunct professor of intelligence
studies at the Helm School of Government
at Liberty University. And so I worked I
worked alongside a a senior professor
had been there 30 years but who had also
been a CIA officer early in his career.
He showed me the final exam that he gave
his students one day and it was such a
powerful exam. It has stuck in my mind
all these years. It was just a handful
of questions. So he the first question
he he put on the board um you have
captured a bonafide terrorist. You know
that a bomb is going to go off in a
major American city. You have 2 hours to
get the information and diffuse the
bomb. Do you torture this man? Yes. No.
Explain yourself.
That was 15 minutes. 15 minutes later,
the guy is a true believer. He didn't
give you anything. But you have his wife
in custody. Do you beat his wife in
front of him just to get him to give you
the the information? Remember, American
lives are on the line. Yes. No. Explain
yourself. The third question is, the
wife's a true believer, too, but you
have their children in custody. Do you
beat the children or threaten to beat
the children? Yes. No. Explain yourself.
>> Where do you draw the fourth question?
>> Yeah. The fourth question was you've
died and you're at the gates of heaven
and Peter uh refers you to God himself
and he says
now you explain yourself.
What do you tell him?
>> Do we do that stuff?
>> Do we beat people's children in front of
them? [sighs]
>> We we've certainly threatened to do
worse than just beat the children. Yes,
we yeah we I I was unaware of any
children being beaten but yes it was
common to threaten to beat the children
and the children are always separated
from the parents so the parents don't
know if the kids are being beaten or not
>> but yeah we would make that threat quite
frequently
>> there's a big gulf between threatening
and doing though
>> um uh when you say uh US laws you know
that was your that was your north star
um so are do you believe today the CIA a
is breaking US laws uh abroad and what
what are the laws that you're most
worried about being violated today?
>> In all honesty, the the US laws that I'm
the most worried about are are laws
surrounding uh the weaponization of
intelligence. I really truly believe
that the CIA was weaponized uh during
the Obama administration especially to
go after the uh the CIA's enemies or the
DNC's enemies. Listen, it it it wasn't I
I blew the whistle on the on the George
W. Bush torture program and the Bush
Justice Department investigated me for a
year from December of '07 to December
of08 and decided in the end that I had
not committed a crime and they dropped
the case. It was the Obama
administration, specifically John
Brennan, who personally asked Eric
Holder to reopen the case against me
secretly. It was the Obama
administration that prosecuted me. And
not just me, eight national security
whistleblowers, which is almost three
times the number of all previous
presidents combined. So, you know, while
the CIA's mandate is to break laws
overseas, I think that they're breaking
laws in the United States.
>> Yeah. One of the concerns I always had
was when we developed these exquisite
tools of deception, mind control, uh,
uh, sigant gathering and processing,
when we develop them abroad, it's human
beings who'd have those skills and those
human beings end up coming and living
back in the United States and a whole
lot of them end up working for
contractors where those tools that were
intended to be used against America's
enemies abroad are visited in these
internal struggles we have we have here.
Uh what is the scale of that do you
think John?
>> I think the scale is huge. The scale is
huge because look at the the the
scandals that have already come to light
in places like Greece or the United Arab
Emirates where where Israeli
um uh software a Pegasus software
specifically has been used
first through a an American contractor
and then through the Israelis directly
uh where it's being used against
Americans. There was a scandal what two
years ago where it was like the American
soccer team or something was being
intercepted in Greece. It it literally
brought down the Greek government.
>> So yeah, we need to be very careful.
>> And so people understand Pegasus because
I got I I got pretty concerned about
this on the judiciary committee. It is a
tool that that will give uh the holder
of the Pegasus technology full access to
your phone and you don't have to take
any action. So you don't have to click a
link, you don't have to mash a button.
They they can use your phone and they
can exploit all the information on it.
They can exploit the camera, the
microphone at any time they want. And so
so uh this was technology that was
developed in Israel. The major
commercial user is the cartels. Uh they
are the major commercial commercial
user. Okay, that's not like government.
Terrifying. And then we found that the
FBI had paid $5 million for this to to
to pick us. And so we we bring
Christopher Ray in and and some of these
guys and say, "Why why is the FBI doing
this?" And their answer was, "We paid $5
million just to test what its
capabilities were um in in the event
that we had to defend against it." In
the event that we had to defend against
it, which I thought was totally bogus at
the time. Um, do you think that this is
going to be PEG do you think Pegasus
will be used to topple other governments
and do you think that there's a there's
a political node to it or is it just
like a a mercenaryized technology?
>> I think it's I think it's more
sophisticated and more broadly spread uh
than than what we know right now. And
one of the one of the terrible things is
that first of all, it's so good. And
like you said, Congressman, you're
exactly right. You don't have to take
any action to activate it on your phone.
You don't have to click a link. You
don't have to respond to a text message
or anything like that. It just works
just like that. And you have no idea. We
wouldn't have known that similar uh
similar software programs were being
used by NSA against American citizens.
It's illegal for NSA to spy on
Americans. It's a part of NSA's charter,
its founding charter, that it can't spy
on Americans. And thanks to Ed Snowden,
we know that, you know, easily 50% of
what NSA does is to spy on Americans.
Well, now when Pegasus or systems akin
to Pegasus are available commercially,
I mean, how how do you protect yourself?
Somebody asked me the other day if there
were any um chat apps that were truly
secure and I I I wanted to give a an
intelligent answer. So I called my
friend Tom Drake, the NSA whistleblower,
and I asked him and he said no. The easy
answer is no. Nothing's secure. Even
Signal, even if it's not true that the
US intelligence community has a backdoor
into Signal, Signal is only encrypted
when you hit the send button. That's
when it encrypts. They can intercept
your message as you're typing it before
you hit send,
>> right?
>> And so it doesn't matter if they can't
break the encryption.
>> So that I kind speaking of Pegasus and
what you just said about Signal, um
because I use Signal and I picked it up
after I did a documentary in 2018 about
the NSA and Obama spying and
surveillance and stuff and that
terrified me. So I got Signal cuz Edward
Snowden recommended it. But is there any
such thing as privacy anymore? Is there
any private communications or any
privacy in your life that you would
reasonably expect? President Trump
signed the order to end the looney's war
on crypto. And with the Genius Act now
law, America is officially the crypto
capital of the world. I'm not just
talking about this. I am a client of
Block Trust IRA. They're powered by the
world's number one animus AI platform.
It's the same elite technology once
reserved for the big guys on Wall
Street. Now, it's been repurposed for
Patriots through our partnership. While
other systems just hold and hope, this
is an AI investment strategy that
attacks. It turns swings in the market
into opportunity. That's how Block Trust
IRA has outperformed Bitcoin itself by
over 250% since 2020. This is American
innovation for ordinary investors to
work their solutions best for their
families. Don't let prosperity pass you
by. Go to mattcrypto.com
right now. You can even do a full or
partial rollover of IRA funds. That way
you can get into crypto opportunity
without taxing the cash in your bank
account. mattcrypto.com. You can get up
to a $2,500 funding Bitcoin bonus just
to jumpstart your account. Make sure to
check them out today.
>> Okay, that answers that. [laughter]
>> Yeah, I'm sorry. I I hate to say it, but
>> there's no such thing. No, I I'm I'm
just not. I'll tell you I'll tell you
what. Wikileaks, an offshoot of
Wikileaks was working 10 years ago on on
a new chat app that was not just
encrypted, but where the where the chat
would disappear
like after I think it was 30 seconds of
of disuse, right? So, you finish your
chat, you've exchanged your messages,
and then poof, 30 seconds later would
just disappear. but they couldn't get
past this notion that it can be
intercepted before it's encrypted.
Nobody can figure out how to get around
that.
>> One of the things that um was frequently
debated in in the back rooms in in
Congress was this blend of investment
into signals intelligence exploitation
versus human intelligence exploitation.
And uh you know, you'd get the the the
wizards of of tech to say, "Look, all
this human stuff is all like the stuff
of the Cold War 80s. Everything we're
going to need, we're going to be able to
exploit with signals intelligence." What
do you think is the right blend? And is
there any is there any experience you've
had that might be a cautionary tale to
those who would deplete some of the
human capabilities in service of of
these uh sant ambitions?
>> That's a great question. That's a that's
a not just an important question, but I
think it's the most important question
for any incoming new CIA director. Uh,
SIGant is not going to save the day.
Yes, sigant is great. You can grab every
every phone call, every text message,
every email out of the air and put it in
your giant Cray computers in the Utah
desert and have it sit there for 500
years until you need it. That's great.
But Sigant isn't going to be inside the
room when Saddam Hussein makes a
decision to invade Kuwait or when,
[clears throat] you know, the Chinese
decide to go to war with India over
their border or Vladimir Putin makes the
decision to invade Ukraine. You have to
get that information from a human
source. And every new incoming CIA
director says, "It's time to get back to
basics. We're going to rely on human
intelligence. Our job is to recruit
spies to steal secrets." Everybody says
that and then you know they they get
distracted by these you know shiny
objects called signals intelligence and
uh and they walk away from human
intelligence
>> and and what do you think is the cost of
that ultimately?
Oh, ultimately we don't know that the
Berlin Wall is coming down, that Israel
is on the verge of attacking uh Iran and
they've made the decision to do so, that
Saddam is going to invade uh Kuwait. Any
of these these momentous
global events were missed by the CIA for
the most part. I mean, analytically,
yeah, we made the the judgment that
Saddam was going to invade Kuwait. Yes,
we made the analytic judgment that that
Putin was going to uh invade Ukraine,
but you got to have somebody in the room
who can report back to you so you know
exactly what the the thought process is.
And that helps the president to create
his own policy to counter whatever the
decision was. It's always surprised me
how how many foreign officials the CIA
really did control um either through I
mean and sometimes like payment
sometimes um just uh foreign officials
admiration for the United States and
they would love to know who the station
chief was. They would love to be you
know having meetings with the embassy
and and talking about stuff. How would
you describe to our audience um the
scale, scope, and meaning of the United
States government basically having
foreign officials doing our bidding by
hook or by crook?
I was at a cocktail party once, a
diplomatic cocktail party, and uh and I
met a guy who I immediately recognized
as a former prime minister.
And I thought, "Oh my god, he's a former
prime minister. Now he's a member of not
just a member, he's a founder of a of a
less populous less popular party. He's
probably not going to be prime minister
again, but maybe he will be. Who knows?"
So I rush back to the embassy. I fill
out a a template for this cable and I
say, "Hey, I met this I met the former
prime minister. Give me a name trace on
him. Looking for any vulnerabilities.
I'm going to invite him to dinner. I'm
going to try to get him.
And then they send me a cable back the
next day and they said, "Cease and
desist. He's been ours since the 70s."
[laughter]
And and and is that is that largely
maintained through through financial
distributions that like what what what
is the what is the waterfall of of uh
choices that you make when you're when
you're
>> turning someone like that?
>> Blackmail. Let me let me address
blackmail because that's important.
People raise this with me literally
every single day. The CIA doesn't
blackmail. Um we used to, but they they
haven't done that since the 70s. Uh
because it's not effective in order to
really squeeze great information out of
a source. The source has to love you.
The source has to think that you're his
best friend. that sure, you know, you're
doing it, you guys are doing this
because you're paying him, but but
really it's because you're in a bromance
and he loves hanging out with you and
he's going to give you the plans to the
the new generation Russian tank just
because he loves you. Um,
studies have been done about this
internally at the CIA. 95% of these
relationships are based on cash
exchanges.
Simple as that. We have money. You need
the money. I'm happy to give you
whatever money you want so long as you
give me the information I want. And we
shake hands. You sign this ridiculous
little contract that I made up in MSWord
and uh and everybody's happy.
The other 5% is interesting. The other
5% is ideology. Sometimes they just love
love love the United States. Sometimes
it's excitement because they've seen all
the James Bond movies and the Jack
Reacher movies and all these others and
they just want to experience the
excitement of the clandestinity of these
operations. Sometimes it's revenge. They
got passed over for promotion. They're
angry [clears throat] at their bosses
and they just want to screw the boss.
And so by God, they're going to they're
going to reach out to the CIA and
they're going to volunteer. But 95% of
it is money. It's a cash transaction.
And if you, you know, let's say you have
access to the local Communist Party,
that might be good for $23,000
a month. But if you're going to give me
Osama bin Laden, I'm going to give you
25 million, $50 million, and I'll give
it to you in cash, in gold, in diamonds,
in Bitcoin. I'll give it to you any way
you want to receive it. If you want it
in land, I'll give it to you in land.
And just because I'm a nice guy and I
like your face, I'm willing to resettle
you in any country in the world where
you would like to live.
>> How do we get access to those uh to to
those different asset classes to
redistribute in exchange for
information?
>> Yeah, that's also a great question. And
you know, early on in my career, uh, the
instructors told all of us that the best
agents that you will ever recruit are
going to be people you had never heard
of who are just going to walk into the
American embassy and say, "I want to
speak to a CIA officer." Like for
example, I can't name an Iranian nuclear
scientist, and I follow the issue. I
can't name a single one of them. But if
one of them walks into the American
embassy in Vienna, Austria, because he
happens to be in town to attend some
seminar,
I'm going to grab him and that
recruitment is going to make my career.
I'm going to send him back with some
sort of listening device that he can use
to issue burst transmissions and send me
classified reports on the Iranian
nuclear program.
>> Wow.
>> U But
>> does that happen the other way, John?
Because you did you did counter
intelligence work, too. uh talk to talk
to the uh frequency, scope, and concern
about other countries using these exact
tools you've described, bribes, um
ideology, whatever, to to get our our
our countrymen to to do their bidding.
Good.
>> Well, there was that story that just
came out about I think it was the Air
Force pilot who was giving our
information over.
>> Well, no, he was training the Chinese on
on uh
>> Yeah, he was training the Chinese.
>> My guess is he wasn't a volunteer.
>> Probably not. No, I I don't think it was
a volunteer. I can't get my glasses
straight. No, I don't think it was a
volunteer. Uh, but you're right. You
know, other countries aren't stupid.
These are not secret techniques that
we're using. We're just trying to
exploit human nature. And so certainly
there are there are other intelligence
services that are actively trying to
recruit Americans. It's a little recruit
CIA.
>> Well, hold on.
Rate the ones that are the best at
getting our people to flip.
>> Is it MI6? Israel. Yeah.
>> Well, hold on. No. In order. Okay. Go
ahead.
>> Okay. In order. In order. I would say
the Israelis.
Number one.
>> They're our greatest ally. Why would Why
would Why would they be trying to get
our people to flip?
>> Right. You know, the thing about the
Israelis um and and I'm not talking just
about Jonathan Pard. That's that's
ancient history. My very first day at
the CIA. The very first day, the first
thing we did is we stood up, we put our
hands in the air and we swore to uphold
the constitution and to protect it
against all enemies, domestic and
foreign.
And then we got a briefing by the
director of security for the whole CIA.
Now granted, this is 36 years ago, but
but it it is, you know, still current.
And he said, "Our greatest challenge as
individual officers was going to be
counter intelligence because there are
going to be temptations out there and
our friends and our enemies are going to
try to exploit our own vulnerabilities.
Do you drink maybe to excess a little
bit? Do you like to gamble? You know,
whatever the problem is, tell us now so
we can help you work your way through
it." But he said that day that the
Israelis have two declared intelligence
officers at the Israeli embassy in
Washington. One from Mossad and one from
Shinbet. Shinbet being the domestic uh
intelligence service akin to the FBI.
and he said the FBI has been able to
identify
187 undeclared Israeli intelligence
officers spread all across the United
States actively trying to recruit
employees of our defense contractors and
I'll give you an example why we
developed the F-35 and the Israelis were
the first ones they said we want the
F-35 we said sure we'll give you the
F-35 we're going to slightly degrade the
avionics just slightly just so that god
forbid if one gets shot down the
Russians or the Chinese can't take it
and reverse engineer it. We're going to
call it the F-35i for Israel. They said,
"No, no, we want the F-35 and with the
same one you have." We said, "No, we'll
give you the F-35i." In the meantime,
the Emiratis came to us and they said,
"We want this F-35." We said, "Great.
We're going to slightly degrade the
avionics. We'll call it the F-35E for
Emirates and we'll sell you that." They
said, "Great, we'll take it."
The Israelis have been out there trying
to steal the F-35 avionics ever since we
said the word F-35
because they really believe that at the
end of the day they stand alone against
the rest of the world. And if we're not
going to give them literally everything
that they say they want, then by God
they're going to recruit spies and
they're going to steal it from us.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> And this is worse than what China does.
The Chinese are very very laser focused,
no pun intended, on technology.
The thing is is the Chinese don't really
have a a a true understanding and
appreciation of American culture. So the
Chinese will walk up to you and say, "I
will give you money. You give me
technology." And you know, there's no
like there's no, you know, at least buy
me a drink first. Yeah.
>> Right.
>> Yeah.
>> There's none of that. The Russians have
a long view. They're they're quite good
at it, too. Um,
>> are they the second best?
>> Yeah, the Russians. I I would put the
Russians at second best.
>> The Cubans are third best.
>> The Cubans
>> really, I would think UK.
>> Cubans are good.
>> Cubans are very, very good. In fact, um,
the the CIA has never recruited a Cuban
who didn't turn out to be a double
agent.
>> That says something. Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> Well, well, the Cubans don't
operationalize the intelligence. They're
just a marketplace for it. They they
have commoditized it. Pearson, I
promised that you would get some
questions about current events. I could
talk for hours about the intelligence,
John, but but but please go ahead.
>> So, heading heading into this interview,
I was doing some research and um I was
reading about some former CIA
operations. Uh you obviously know about
Operation Ajax uh in 1953 in Iran where
we overthrew the government. Um well,
then we have also operation PB Success
in 1954 in Guatemala where we overthrew
the government. operation in Congo uh
where we overthrew Patrice Lamumba 1965
operation in Chile where we overthrew
the president uh Salvador Alende um and
now we're seeing a lot of things
happening in Iran um that well in
operation Ajax we had um the CIA funded
anti-government protests
>> we had paid journalists to publish
propaganda we had CIA backed street mobs
rioting in the streets
And all this is just seeming very
familiar. And I'm just wondering from
your perspective if you think that what
we're seeing right now is another CIA
operation.
>> Yeah, I think it is. I think it's more
um a joint MOSSAD CIA operation. And the
only reason I say that is because the
Mossad has bragged about it in the
Israeli press.
>> Yeah. that they were working with the
MEK, the Mujahedin Khulk, formerly a a
terrorist group, and u they were able to
lightly arm the MEK. Uh they were able
to get MEK operatives in Iran to set
fire to mosques and then to burn 38 fire
trucks. So there was no way to put out
the the fires at the mosques. So the
Israelis were they couldn't help
themselves but to brag about it in um in
the Israeli media what 2 3 weeks ago. I
think that look, history has proven that
it is it's easier, it's cheaper, and
it's safer for Americans if you let
controlled mobs do your dirty work
rather than putting your own operatives
on the ground and, you know, carrying
out close-in assassinations and things
like that. The risk is just too high for
something like that. And so to answer
your question, yeah, there's a long
history, as you as you correctly noted,
there's a long history of the CIA doing
things like this. I've got to tell you,
the Guatemala operation is one of my
favorite to talk about because it is so
outrageous. There's a long history.
>> There's a long history that went into
that operation in Guatemala that started
actually before there was anything
called a CIA. It started in the late
19th century. There was an American
railroad tycoon who bought a narrow
strip of land from from Guatemala City
to the coast with the idea being that he
could transport goods from the coast to
Guatemala City and make money being the
the sole way of transporting these
goods. So they hired, you know, local
indigenous people to lay the track. And
he went down there to uh just to take a
look at his investment, watch them lay
the track. And every day at lunchtime,
the workers would take a break and they
would pick these fruits off of the trees
and they would eat the fruits. And so
the tycoon said, "What are these fruits
that uh that the workers are eating?"
And he was told, "They're called
bananas." He had never seen a banana
before. He had never heard of a banana.
So he tried one and it was delicious and
sweet and he said we should take the
bananas and send them to America and he
did and got even richer than he always
was. He also changed the name of the
company to the United Fruit Company.
Well this went for the next 3/4 of a
century and finally in 1954
uh the Guatemalan government said you
know we're sending all these bananas to
the United States. We're not making any
money on these bananas at all. The
United Fruit Company owns the the train.
It owns the tracks. It owns the land on
the two side of the tracks where all the
bananas are growing. We're not making
anything on this. We should nationalize
the bananas.
Well, three of the members of the board
of directors of theiteiite of the United
Fruit Company were John Foster Dulles,
the secretary of state, Alan Dulles, his
brother, the CIA director, and President
Eisenhower's secretar's brother.
And so, we overthrew the Guatemalan
government. We installed a military
dictatorship that brutalized the
population for the next 20 plus years.
And that country still hasn't gotten
over that coup. It's still one of the
most dangerous places in the world. I
went to Guatemala a couple of years ago
to volunteer for a couple of weeks at an
orphanage. And thank God that the
orphanage had a 20 foot high concrete
wall all the way around it because I
could barely get to sleep at night for
all the gunfire outside.
>> Oh jeez.
>> It's still a terrible place. And it's
terrible place because we made it that
way.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. We don't have a great record of
overthrowing these governments and
having positive. really don't, you know,
we're we're good at overthrowing.
>> I thought there would be more like
United Fruit, Standard Fruit resentment
over our Venezuela operation. I spent a
lot of time in Latin America. I covered
Latin America extensively. I I I thought
that that would sort of tickle those um
frustrations of yester year. And I'm
surprised it didn't. Uh almost everyone
I know in Latin America was thrilled
that Maduro was removed. And I I did
ask, you know, the question is, is this
is this a precedent that that we're
going to be excited about when Democrats
are in power? Like, are they is is like
a future president AOC going to order
Delta Force to go and like yank Javier
Malay out of [laughter] Argentina if she
doesn't doesn't like, you know, the fact
that he fired teachers who were trying
to teach pronouns. I I don't know.
>> You're absolutely right.
>> I I have burned my hour with uh with
John. Did you have any Any any final
questions?
>> Yeah, one one final question. We talked
about privacy before. There's the the
popular myth that the CIA knows all and
sees all and is in your phone and in
your email and watching through your TV,
uh, knows everything that you're doing.
But we constantly see cases where
there's domestic terrorism or someone
goes out and kills somebody and has been
texting with people and posting on
forums and leaving a trail that you'd
think would be caught. So, how really
omnipotent is the CIA? are these
agencies and how much of that is just
popular mythos
>> and and I guess how much of it is
allowed to happen?
>> Now that's the $64,000 question right
there. Um they're not omnipotent. Their
computer systems are near omnipotent,
but you don't have a human being that's
going over all this this data. You know,
it's it yes, it's all being collected.
It's all being just pulled out of the
ether and stored in these computers, but
human beings don't actually look at it
until after the fact. Look at the San
Bernardino attack from whatever it was,
2017 or 2016. The the
terrorists in that case in San
Bernardino, California, were
communicating through the chat function
of a game app. Well, I'll tell you who
pioneered that was was the Mossad.
That's how they would communicate in
their anti-Hzbala operations. Um, but
the FBI, it never occurred to the FBI
that they should be working with NSA to
to collect, you know, in-game chat apps.
I mean, who would even think of such a
thing? So, yeah, the information is out
there. It's just not necessarily being
seen by a human being. for the CIA. I
mean, the CIA will tell you right off
the bat um that they recruit spies to
steal secrets and they only do that
overseas. Okay, I want to believe that.
I'm not sure that I do. But I would be
more worried domestically, far more
worried about NSA and FBI. And one other
thing about FBI that I think we should
be worried about for for you know 250
years practically, well not 250 since
the FBI was founded in the early 1920s.
If they wanted information, personal
information on an American or from an
American, they had to get a warrant.
Right. You have to go before a judge.
You have to have probable cause. You
have to do it with a warrant. They don't
anymore for a while. Right. Right. Yeah.
Right. After 911, they FISA number one.
Number two, right after 911, they
started using these things called
national security letters, which were
just like threatening letters to the to
the ISP providers saying, "We're the FBI
and you're not, and we want this
information, and you have 48 hours to to
cough it up." Okay, that's not a
warrant. If hearing all these crazy
stories about spycraft is making you
think that there might be turbulence
ahead, buy gold. I'm betting my family's
financial future on asset classes that
have stood the test of time. Lear
Capital has all the information ready
for you to make the right choice for
your goals. So, if you want that
information, you go to leermat.com.
They've got everything ready for you.
lermat.com
and you will be partnered with the
leader in precious metals investing.
They will get you educated and they are
the only folks that have a 24-hour
satisfaction guarantee. You can get your
money back if necessary. Nobody else has
this, but the customer service is so
great. You're going to get the investor
guides, the report, you're going to see
the durable value of gold and silver,
and you'll see what people are saying
about the potential ahead.
Protect your family's financial future
now. Call 800511-3700.
That's 800511-3700.
Number three,
the the social media platforms sell our
metadata to anybody who wants to pay.
And so why would the FBI go before a
judge and have to make a a probable
cause argument when they can just go to
Meta and just buy it?
>> We we we tried to pass laws to say that
the uh that the FBI could not buy like
use data brokers to get information that
would otherwise require a warrant. And I
mean you might you might as well have
been cheerleading the fall of the Twin
Towers making that suggestion. people
were saying, "Oh, we're going to have
the next 911. The blood's going to be on
your hands." We uh I pursued that along
with some of the some of the folks like
Daryl Isa and and we totally lost that
legislative effort. But the national
security letters, guess who's receiving
those letters at the big tech companies,
former FBI leadership,
>> right? If you f if you follow the
revolving door between FBI, CIA, and big
tech, that's where they go to cash out.
And so it's a it's a CIA FBI person
writing a letter to someone who months
before was a CIA FBI person and you're
just the deliverable. You you the
American public. What a cheery note to
end on. Uh John Kuryaku, we always
appreciate your uh your insights, your
perspective, your expertise. Uh it's
added so much to our network and our
program to introduce you to our viewers
and uh and we wish you well and hope we
check back with you soon. Pleasure. I
look forward to it. We'll get you next.
Uh, what what a discussion. So, long
story short, we are the bad guys.
[laughter]
>> We're just going to change the name of
this podcast to Pearson Sharp is not
satisfied.
>> Like I said yesterday, are you
satisfied?
>> Never. Thanks for joining me, but we'll
be back next week to be unsatisfied
together.
>> Want to see more great videos like this?
Click on the link below to subscribe to
Oen Live and watch Dan Ball's Real
America and the Matt Gate Show on Dish
Channel 212. Tune in, subscribe, and
watch today.